[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
cool all right welcome everyone to the
stoa
uh i'm peter limberg the steward of the
stoa it still has a place for us to
cohere and dialogue about what matters
most at the knife's edge of this very
moment
and today we got richard d bartlett and
ronan harrington
uh richard is the co-founder of lumio
the the hum
and in spiral he's an overall bottle of
awesomeness
and ronan harrington a system changer
whose mind is always on the future and
he's the founder of
alter ego and currently works for
rethink x
uh and true story uh when i was on this
podcast circuit in
2018 everyone's inviting me on podcasts
ronan actually took my podcast virginity
so thank you sir it was the very first
podcast i was on
um and so how today uh came about
uh richard wanted to test a field test
uh
a workshop and any time richard asks me
for for
anything you know i might bring short
circuits and i just say yes so
we are here um so i'm just gonna uh
tag in uh richard and ronan and they're
gonna kind of uh
walk us through the workshop today which
is about obviously depolarizing
conversations um so i will unmute
everyone uh or give everyone access to a
mute i'll take richard in
give him sharing permission and um i
believe you want to do some check-ins
all right so i'll i'll mute you guys um
let me go first with the check-ins yeah
go on
all right check-ins um
i feel a little self-conscious maybe
five percent
uh but just sort of like almost like
about to jump on a wave of calmness
if waves can become
um as for me um
i'm right here on the brink i'm i'm
sitting on the fence between
uh anxiety which is like
oh god uh this is new this is
the first time i'm trying a thing and
it'll be okay
but it won't be as good as i want it to
be and i don't like that part of the
learning curve
it makes me feel small and silly um
but that's only one side of the fence
the other side is like uh
enthusiasm and excitement and the um
embodied experience of that is confusing
whether i'm anxious or excited so i'm
like trying to convince myself that no
it's just excitement and this is going
to be great
so that's me a bit giddy and happy to
have some homies in the room with me
it's really
really happy to see you all how are you
doing ronan
um i'm not really sure i'm basically uh
i i live in the uk countryside so i'm
just
off a three-hour train on transit to an
another train to go to france this
gathering rich and i are running this
alter-ego gathering so i feel kind of
like
like mid-travel and i've uh scrambled
into
a delightfully quiet cafe to do this
workshop so i feel
quite ungrounded but uh like
delightfully unattached
and um just really a big fan of peter
and co of what you're doing and it's
just amazing that people are gathering
in the middle of the day just to chat
about what go on so i uh
yeah i'm really happy and i think we've
got something interesting and i'm really
happy to share it with you
um peter before i forget it's really
important that we just record the start
but and not the second bit
when we're asking people to be sharing
things so
um i'm gonna try and and do the
the the smallest version of the lengthy
lecture that i have been
summoning in my head for the last few
days of like all of these different
ideas
and just give the like uh essential
pieces of it
and what i'd like us to do is basically
a bit of setup and then some practices
and there's going to be one practice
which is
your own private reflection so i'm going
to bring you some questions and you're
going to think about them
um and take notes get a notebook or
write on the computer whatever just have
your own private process
and then the second part will be an
opportunity for us to
practice having a conversation and it's
a conversation that
um hopefully has some polarities in it
has some tension has some like
um energy and enthusiasm in it that
could get difficult and we're going to
practice like how do we hold that
tension in a generative way
that's what we're going to try to do and
it's it's the kind of thing where
you can hang back and it's you're not
going to be pressured to participate
it's going to be fine
so um the the kind of conceptual
uh con the the content that i wanted to
just
put into the room to have some kind of
shared starting point
um ronan mentioned alter ego it's a
network of social change people
political people
and we are
we're trying to become better versions
of ourselves so that we do a better kind
of social change
i guess like how do we grow up how do we
support each other to grow up and
and be more mature and um
make better generative happier more
curious
change and one of the dynamics that gets
in the way of that
is um how we show up in groups and so
that's my real
um curiosity is like how how does this
person called me show up when i'm in a
group and what kind of
social reflex do i reflexes do i have
like how do those reflexes
change my behavior and and can i become
more aware of them and and
maybe show up in a more mature way
so the conceptual piece that really blew
my mind actually
came from peter so i'm going to start
there
we'll share this if you haven't read
this white paper by peter and
conor barnes i i recommend this
every couple of weeks to a new person
the memetic tribes of culture war 2.0
and it's a long read and it's it's worth
it it's from 2018
and um two years on it's still got a
huge amount of
material in there that um both ronan and
i
feel very resourced by and it's really
informing like how do we do the work
that we do in the world
and i'm not going to try and summarize
the 38 minute read but
there's a piece in the middle which i
want to look into with some depth which
is
this table beautiful spreadsheet
and anyone who knows me knows that
spreadsheet's in my happy place
so what this table is attempting to to
show
is what peter calls memetic tribes
so down the left left-hand side we have
this list of different tribes
um and then across each row we have some
properties about these tribes so
this map is not attempting to be
accurate or
comprehensive but just to give a name to
some of the different groups that are
currently active online
um like the social justice activists who
i for instance identify with
and what are we doing we're trying to
end oppression and what are our values
and where do we meet
um what kind of identities do we
prioritize
and we
when i saw this list um this
non-complete list of all these different
tribes it was like
um yeah like going from a view of oh
there's this planet called earth
to realizing there's this whole universe
or potentially a multiverse
of tons of different solar systems and
like each one of these rows
has thousands of well potentially
millions of people some of them
they have a really comprehensive sense
of purpose and mission in the world
they prioritize a different set of
values they have different meeting
places different
sources of media that they're paying
attention to different heroes
they've got really unique language you
know the way that they
um describe themselves and the way that
they make sense of the world is quite
unique and a lot of times
um the languages
that maybe they're all speaking english
but in a way where it's very difficult
even to have a shared understanding
about what
what you're talking about and and so
this is the context in which we're
organizing this is the context in which
we're
like we're pulling together these social
change activists who are trying to make
the world better
and we have to
pay attention to the tribe that we're in
and
the the tendencies that we have towards
a really toxic kind of tribalism
and that's i mean that's really a huge
focus of mine in general so
we have options i think like
when we're in when we find ourselves
positioned somewhere on this table or
and i'm sure none of us will feel like
oh yes this totally gets me you've got
me i'm perfectly i'm one of these new
atheists you've got me here but
um this idea that we are in some kind of
in-group i think there's a
we have an option we have a possibility
about which posture how do we occupy
that space
so on the one option we have a what i
call ideological micronationalism
so this is um this is the worst side
of our in-group and out-group dynamic so
this is like
um our beliefs are the right beliefs we
understand what's happening in the world
and we're right
um therefore
our people are unique and superior and
therefore you know you should listen to
us
uh we should be kind of in a position of
leading the rest of
all the other people and everyone else
really like we should be in a fight with
them
um either either because we want to
conquer them or we're going to try and
convert them
and if if they really knew um how the
world works they'd understand that we
were right all along
so that's kind of like the worst posture
i think that we can take and what we're
trying to do with alterigo and with this
process that we're
going to play with today is find a
different posture which is not like a
nationalist posture but something that's
more pluralistic
and we've been playing with this idea of
complicated majorities
and that's a phrase that i picked up
from some activists in barcelona i also
saw it repeated in
taiwan as well and it's this idea of
we're heading into a future
that is going to be drastically
different and it's either going to be
drastically different because
we've run out of energy and um the
nation state has disintegrated
or it's going to be different because
we've figured out how to have a
thriving and just and equitable and
sustainable society either way it's kind
of
we're undergoing a lot of change and
we'd like that change to be
done democratically and therefore we
need a complicated majority to achieve
it that means we
need to be able to step outside of our
little row on the table
instead of just being us you know like
our crew is mostly a bit of here
a bit of here some of this i'm an
occupier so that's me
instead of me and my crew kind of taking
over the world we actually have to learn
how to
build complicated majorities with some
of the others
so how do we do that i mean this is the
big puzzle and we don't know but this is
what you've
been invited to work it out with us i
think
a big part of it has got to do with
curiosity so it's like
being curious about what we don't know
rather than being so attached to what we
do know and how we're so certain about
how the world's going and our beliefs
are the right ones we're actually
cultivating intentionally our curiosity
about the unknown
and that curiosity extends to other
people not that we don't assume that
they are stupid and wrong
and just needing to be converted we
assume that they
have had distinct experiences which have
led to them having different values and
beliefs and maybe a posture of curiosity
could open up
a genuine relationship maybe i could
learn something maybe we would change
each other's mind if we allowed each
other to really
open up to a genuine conversation and
there's a kind of internal curiosity
that happens as well which is about
paying attention to our own motivations
and emotions in our social reflexes like
what is it that is
am i purely being driven because i want
to see a socially just world or is there
also some of my own stuff around
belonging
and um my psychology and my emotions
also playing out in that
in that process so we want to try and
like unpick some of that
i really don't like presenting to a
screen it's much nicer to stop sharing
and now see all your faces again
so i want to get into a practice
because this is the
like i can i can practice um i can do
the tell but what we need is the show i
reckon
and and and to learn how do we do this
together
so there's the first phase which is
going to be an invitation for you to
just
write some notes for yourself in silence
and
um i've got some questions to get that
ball rolling
ronan if you feel like um we need to add
extra questions or prompts please just
jump in and do it but just just to get
the ball rolling
what i want you to be thinking about is
what are some of the
in-groups or the tribes or the
collective identities that you're
currently affiliated with
like when you looked at that list where
there's something like yeah i'm kind of
there so i'm
i'm definitely this or i'm kind of a bit
there
and can you think about what are some of
your own
doubts or like other thoughts that you
would withhold from those groups because
of the risk of being judged or
ostracized or you're like
i mean i'm part of that collective but i
wouldn't want them to know this about me
so i think we start there and then i'll
add you some more prompts
um maybe it's just helpful as a prompt
and